Welcome and good to be in the middle of פסחים Psachim and
I want to again thank Michael for his for really and רבקה
Rivka for covering me when I was gone.
And who? The Weinstock? Okay so we pick up now at the
bottom today's דף daf is זיין zayin seven and we pick up
at the bottom where is talking about the principle of הבודק צריך
שיבטל. habodek tzarich sheyevatel. So I know that Michael said that he
gave a good amount of introduction, you'll excuse me I'll just give
try to do my own five minute introduction because I feel I
need to do it for my own sake so you can just
listen if this is all repetition then so be it. So I
just want to say a few principles that we're dealing with here
in the beginning of the מסכת masechet and one particularly surrounding the
issue of ביטול bitul and הבודק צריך שיבטל. habodek tzarich sheyevatel. So
I understand that Michael dealt with you yesterday about this מחלוקת machloket
about how ביטול bitul works. In a number of places where the
גמרא gemara says that ביטול בעלמא סגי bitul b'alma sagi just doing
ביטול bitul suffices רש"י Rashi says because the Torah says תשביתו tashbishu
and therefore by doing ביטול bitul you did תשביתו. tashbishu. That somehow
the act of doing ביטול bitul and saying that it's like you
know you're negating it is considered a fulfillment of that מצווה mitzvah
of תשביתו tashbishu and somehow the implication being that if you fulfill
תשביתו tashbishu like a psychological תשביתו tashbishu not a physical תשביתו tashbishu
but for you it's nothing you know then then obviously if once
you've done that you can't be over on בל יראה ובל ימצא.
bal yera'eh u'bal yimatzeh. Even though like you know technically speaking according
to רש"י Rashi you could say well you still technically do own
it but somehow somehow that it focuses on that act of ביטול
bitul and then you're off the hook for בל יראה ובל ימצא.
bal yera'eh u'bal yimatzeh. That's what רש"י Rashi seems to emphasize. תוספות
Tosafot does not like that and תוספות Tosafot says the only way
you get out of being over on בל יראה ובל ימצא bal
yera'eh u'bal yimatzeh is by making it not yours. And therefore for
תוספות Tosafot the way תשביתו tashbishu works is it's basically a form
of הפקר. hefker. You're basically saying והוי כהפקר v'havei k'hefker it's not
mine you're making it הפקר. hefker. This leads to problems because there's
some גמרות gemaras that say you might need three people present to
make הפקר hefker but nevertheless that's what תוספות Tosafot says. הר"ן The
Ran has a way of if you would integrating רש"י Rashi and
תוספות Tosafot or maybe a variation of תוספות Tosafot and he says
it is true you don't own it. But he says here's how
you don't own it not through an act of הפקר hefker but
because the Torah says and it's a גמרא gemara we just read
I believe yesterday right no two days ago yes two days ago
that the Torah made חמץ chametz חמץ chametz you know is not
in your possession technically you don't own חמץ chametz but if you
have it in your possession you're over on בל יראה ובל ימצא.
bal yera'eh u'bal yimatzeh. Why technically don't you own it? Presumably since
something that you can't get any benefit from and it's worthless whatever
what does ownership mean if there's no way to get any benefit.
So this is a general discussion whether איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah objects
forbidden in benefit have בעלות ba'alut have ownership or not. The simple
sense of the גמרא gemara is that they do not. But nevertheless
if you were the holding it owning it the second before it
became אסור asur then you're חייב. chayav. So הר"ן the Ran says
aha so this is how you get out of בל יראה ובל
ימצא. bal yera'eh u'bal yimatzeh. This is how ביטול bitul works. Because
it's already not going to be yours. So all you've got to
do is just indicate when יום טוב yom tov starts that you're
not interested in it and since you've indicated that you don't want
it and you're not interested in it then it automatically becomes not
yours because it becomes אסור בהנאה asur b'hana'ah and the Torah doesn't
ascribe it to you because you've indicated you're not interested in it.
So you're sort of the detachment from it comes naturally because it's
אסור בהנאה. asur b'hana'ah. The only point is that if you were
actively like trying to possess it you know or implicitly possessing it
you're held responsible. That's the עבירה averah of בל יראה ובל ימצא
bal yera'eh u'bal yimatzeh when you remove your hands you are no
longer responsible. So it's a similar idea of not being yours but
it's more like not sort of showing possession of it because for
technical reason it's not yours anyway. So those are the range of
opinions about how ביטול bitul works number one. And I'll use I'll
get back in a minute to the גמרא gemara discussion about גלוסקא
יפה gluska yafeh which I know was
was Michael was asking. I want to say one other word though
about or a few other words about בל יראה ובל ימצא bal
yera'eh u'bal yimatzeh in terms of this introduction. Why do we do
בדיקה? bedika? I don't know if this was discussed at the also.
The very first משנה mishna you do בדיקה bedika הבודק צריך שיבטל
habodek tzarich sheyevatel why do you do בדיקה? bedika? So the first
רש"י Rashi in the on the משנה mishna says you do בדיקה
bedika not to be over on בל יראה ובל ימצא bal yera'eh
u'bal yimatzeh cause you don't want חמץ chametz in your house. So
תוספות Tosafot says that can't be the reason because the גמרא gemara
says הבודק צריך שיבטל habodek tzarich sheyevatel and ביטול bitul suffices so
you're already not over on בל יראה ובל ימצא. bal yera'eh u'bal
yimatzeh. Now before we get to תוספות Tosafot answer the real answer
to רש"י Rashi is the real answer is that רש"י Rashi is
right because רש"י Rashi is explaining the משנה. mishna. If you look
through all of the משניות mishnayot you will not find ביטול bitul
discussed at all with the one exception of somebody who is on
his way to bring his קרבן פסח korban pesach or to give
a ברית מילה bris milah to his son and it's ערב פסח
erev pesach and he realizes that he left חמץ chametz back in
his house and he can't run back and clean it out so
what does he do? He מבטל. mevattel. Okay that's what the one
משנה mishna is that discusses ביטול. bitul. Other than that the משניות
mishnayot don't discuss ביטול bitul at all. So from the משנה mishna
perspective ביטול bitul is actually a בדיעבד bedieved way it's like the
weak way of fulfilling getting rid of your חמץ. chametz. The real
way is you really check and you get rid of it. ביטול
bitul is something we let you do if somehow time ran out
and you don't have any other options. So רש"י's Rashi right. From
the משנה's Mishnah perspective, the reason you do בדיקה bedika is to
physically find and get rid of all of your חמץ. chametz. Later,
the גמרא, Gemara, which you saw yesterday, says, who was it? אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, הבודק צריך שיבטל,
habodek tzarich sheyivatel, introduced this new idea that oh, if ביטול bittel
always works as a בדיעבד, bidieved, let's always do it all the
time, like belt and suspenders. So even though in the time of
the משנה Mishnah you just did בדיקה, bedika, let's throw in a
ביטול bittel too. Why? Because if somehow you happen to miss something,
you got you covered, now you got ביטול. bittel. All right, then
תוספות Tosafot says, okay, but once you've introduced the belt and suspenders,
if you got the suspenders, now who needs the belt? Once you're
doing the ביטול bittel now, why are we still doing the בדיקה?
bedika? It's really not a question in the משנה, Mishnah, it's a
question in after the position of הבודק צריך שיבטל, habodek tzarich sheyivatel,
why are we still doing the בדיקה bedika once you've got ביטול?
bittel? Now if you would have asked me, the easy answer would
have been in order to not make the ביטול bittel a farce,
right? Because if you basically have, now we have the farce in
another way by selling it all, okay, but if you basically have
your closet filled with your bread and your Cheerios and your cereal...
חלה's challah in the...
right. Say, אני מבטל. ani mevattel.
Okay,
so I would have said that's why you gotta do בדיקה, bedika,
not to make the ביטול bittel an entire farce, right?
Exactly. תוספות Tosafot gives another reason. תוספות Tosafot says no, you gotta
do בדיקה bedika because even if you're not over on בל יראה
ובל ימצא, bal yira'eh uval yimatzei, he says you might not technically
be over, but you're gonna have חמץ chametz around in the house.
That's not a good thing. Not because it makes the ביטול bittel
a farce, but just it's in itself not a good thing. Why
is it in itself not a good thing? So תוספות Tosafot has
two reasons. One reason is you'll accidentally come to eat it. Things
that you're normally eat during the rest of the year, it's not
like חזיר chazir you can have in your house because you know
not to eat חזיר. chazir. But חמץ, chametz, you'll not think and
you'll come and eat it, you'll forget that it's פסח. Pesach. That's
one reason. It's just not a good idea to have it around.
And he points to the fact that a number of גמרות Gemarot
speak about a חיוב chiyuv of בדיקה bedika and like the גמרא
Gemara you saw yesterday, you'll come back if you're leaving before פסח,
Pesach, you'll come back and you'll... you might come to eat it.
So since there seems to be that concern of you might come
to eat it, he says that's why we have to do בדיקה
bedika as well. Then he has another reason. His other reason is
just look, the תורה Torah said בל יראה ובל ימצא, bal yira'eh
uval yimatzei, clearly the תורה Torah doesn't want you to have it
around. So even if technically you have fulfilled the מצוה mitzvah by
doing ביטול, bittel, the rabbis still didn't want you to have it
around either. Which means there's some intrinsic problem of חמץ chametz in
the house, even if you're not being עובר over and even if
it's not... you're not gonna come to eat it. Now that actually,
those two... those two
ideas really explain the... what do you call it? The two approaches
to בל יראה ובל ימצא. bal yira'eh uval yimatzei. Because the question
you really could have asked, instead of why do you have to
do בדיקה bedika if you've already done ביטול, bittel, is why do
I care about... why does the תורה Torah say בל יראה ובל
ימצא? bal yira'eh uval yimatzei? Why didn't it just say like all
other things you're not supposed to eat, don't eat חמץ? chametz? And
there actually are two possible explanations to that. One explanation is it's
so serious and it's also, you don't... you know, it's common, you'll
come to eat it, the תורה Torah had to give a safeguard.
So the בל יראה ובל ימצא bal yira'eh uval yimatzei is a
safeguard, the same thing תוספות Tosafot says the בדיקה bedika is a
safeguard: don't have your חמץ chametz around or you won't pay attention
and you'll come to eat from it. The other possibility is you
got it all backwards. It's not like the focus is on eating
חמץ. chametz. The problem is it's חג המצות. Chag HaMatzot. And חג
המצות Chag HaMatzot means there can't be any חמץ chametz around. It's
the opposite of חג המצות. Chag HaMatzot. So that means two things:
don't have חמץ chametz around and don't eat חמץ. chametz. But that's
all part of the nature of the חג chag and the very
presence of חמץ, chametz, even if you won't come to eat from
it, is inherently a problem.
Isn't it a reenactment of the primal experience of the בני ישראל?
Bnei Yisrael?
About not having any חמץ. chametz. Exactly, when they went, right, when
they went... לא חמץ? lo chametz? Exactly,
forget about eating it. It's the presence that's a problem. Well because
if it's a matter of
eating, then if I'm not in my home, then you know...
Ah, so, and I'm not gonna fully expand on this, but I
did want to say, and with this I'll end my little introduction,
that those two ideas, what you got through yesterday, was a whole
discussion about בל יראה ובל ימצא, bal yira'eh uval yimatzei, when the
פסוקים pesukim they're different: it's לא ימצא בבתיכם lo yimatzei bevatteichem and
לא יראה לך בכל גבולך. lo yera'eh lecha bechol gevulecha. And the
גמרא Gemara somehow mashes it all together and makes it all one.
That was yesterday's דף. daf. Okay, but with the פשט pshat of
the פסוקים, pesukim, right, exactly reflect those two different concerns. What did
the גמרא Gemara say? לא ימצא בבתיכם lo yimatzei bevatteichem does not
have the limit of לך. lecha. It doesn't matter whose it is.
And it doesn't matter if it's visible or not visible. The point
is, is that if it's possible that it'll be uncovered and possible
it'll be found. If it's around in your house, I don't care
if it's mine or the non-Jew's. I don't care if it's buried
somewhere or not. If it's possible it'll be exposed and I might
come to eat it, that itself is a problem. So being in
your house is always a problem. However, if it's not in your
house, if it's בכל גבולך, bechol gevulecha, it's out somewhere in the
wider world, so there the problem is not that I'll come to
eat from it. There the problem more is my connection to it.
So my connection to it has to more be לא יראה. lo
yera'eh. I'm seeing it and I'm encountering it, and maybe that's the
לך. lecha. Again, even though there's not a concern of eating it,
but if it's mine and I'm seeing it and I'm connected to
it, that is itself a problem. Even besides the concern of coming
to eat from it. So it's very interesting there might be the
two reasons תוספות Tosafot says why we do בדיקה bedika if we're
doing ביטול bittul could very much reflect two different approaches to בל
יראה ובל ימצא bal yeraeh ubal yimatze and might actually split between
the emphasis of the Torah on לא ימצא lo yimatze and לא
יראה lo yeraeh which for us has become one big איסור. issur.
Okay, so that was my my
little introduction in five minutes which probably should have been fifteen and
should have been on the first דף, daf, but I this is
the first that I'm now teaching doing פסחים Pesachim with you so
I I needed to use that opportunity and it actually does tie
in very much to the issue of הבודק צריך שיבטל. habodek tzarich
sheyevatel. So where we left off, where do we leave off Michael?
Two lines from the bottom.
Two lines from the bottom. דף ד׳. daf daled. Oh no, so
actually this idea of אינה ברשותו של אדם einah birshuto shel adam
wasn't yesterday, wasn't two days ago, was yesterday's דף. daf. Okay, so
now about the דעת עילוי. daat illuy. All right, so I'll so
I'll say one more word about that. So the גמרא Gemara says
so why then do we do the belt and suspenders? If you're
doing בדיקה bedika why do ביטול? bittul? So the גמרא Gemara says
you'll come back and you'll find חמץ chametz ודעתיה עילויה vdaateih illuyeih
and you'll be over on it. So the question is who needs
דעתיה עילויה? daateih illuyeih? Why don't we just say that you'll have
חמץ chametz in your house and you'll be over on it, that
you might have missed something? Okay, so there's a debate here of
רש״י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafot. I'll first give you תוספות's Tosafot's answer.
תוספות Tosafot says דעתיה עילויה daateih illuyeih does not mean a new
special act that you intend to keep it. תוספות Tosafot says דעתיה
עילויה daateih illuyeih all that means is that it's not like פירורין.
perurin. The גמרא Gemara said crumbs are בטל batel automatically, you know,
they're considered just, you know, whatever, the default is you don't want
them. דעתיה עילויה daateih illuyeih is just saying the opposite of the
crumbs. It's just saying let's say there's a nice loaf somewhere that's
buried somewhere and it's not crumbs. So it's not automatically בטל. batel.
And then you missed it and you'll be over on it. So
דעתיה עילויה daateih illuyeih is just saying it's not crumbs, it's not
insignificant and you'll be over on it. Same thing. I know. So
it means so that's what תוספות Tosafot says.
What if you find you find the loaf and you automatically will
say, hmm, what should I do with it?
Right, but according to תוספות, Tosafot, well that's already רש״י, Rashi, but
תוספות Tosafot basically according to תוספות Tosafot it sounds like you don't
even have to find the loaf. The גמרא Gemara could have really
just said you might miss something and it won't be crumbs and
you'll be over. רש״י Rashi makes it sound like you need this
active desire to want it and to keep it and I think
according to רש״י Rashi here's an interesting point. You did a בדיקה,
bedika, so you did a בדיקה, bedika, you were actively searching to
get rid of the חמץ, chametz, right? That in itself indicates you
know not just you want to get rid of this one piece
that you found but you won't want any sort of חמץ chametz
in your house, right? So that might itself create a greater sense
of like detachment from you from the חמץ chametz and it could
be that even if you if you as soon as you see
it if it's clear that you didn't want it it would never
be this עשאן הכתוב כאילו הן ברשותו, asaan hakatuv kailu hen birshuto,
right? It sort of goes back to the ר״ן's Ran's idea. Technically
you don't own it anyway and you were trying to get rid
of it. So you're in this gray area where you were trying
to get rid of it, you didn't actively push it away, but
you clearly weren't so interested in keeping it, you were trying to
get rid of it and maybe therefore if you were to immediately
say 'chametz, burn it', then you would be safe because it technically
wasn't yours. But the second you want it that's an act of
possessing. Okay and that seems
to
be that seems to be רש״י's Rashi's understanding of דעתיה עילויה. daateih
illuyeih. You need that extra amount once you you haven't done ביטול
bittul which would prevent you from doing that without really owning it,
but you haven't done but on the other hand you have been
looking to get rid of it. I'll just tell you one quick
story and then we'll actually transition to the דף daf itself which
is I remember decades ago already, I can't even say years ago,
when I was a when I was a young בחור bachur in
ישיבה yeshiva at גוש עציון. Gush Etzion. הרב ליכטנשטיין Rav Lichtenstein was
talking, they were learning פסחים. Pesachim. And actually I have to admit
I've told the story over so many times I think it happened
to me but it didn't, I heard it from my brother who
was there. He was there a year before me. So anyway the
story was was that they were learning פסחים Pesachim and they were
talking about בדיקה bedika and ביטול bittul and whatever and he told
this story that he was once driving with the רב Rav on
חול המועד chol hamoed and he opened up the the glove compartment
and he saw a Twinkies. Okay, or I think it was a
Devil Dog. So he said, it was פסח, Pesach, right, חול המועד
פסח. chol hamoed Pesach. So he says, he says, 'Oh my God,
what do we do?' So the רב Rav said, 'Burn it!' He
said, 'We can't burn it, we don't own it, we sold it!'
So he said, 'Just burn it!'
So that was the story. So that after it so that after
after the שיעור shiur the Americans and Israelis are all filing out.
So the Israelis are saying, 'What's a Devil Dog?' And the Americans
are saying, 'I didn't know Devil Dogs were kosher!'
But there you go, the idea of the original...
excuse me, the bigger חידוש chiddush would have been the Twinkies.
The Twinkies, that's a big because that's more גוייש goyish than even
a Devil Dog.
And they were never... Were they? And they were never kosher, yeah.
They were really...
I think it was used to be a Devil Dog. All right,
so now let's go on. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Two lines from the bottom. And picking up after that
small or big introduction, the גמרא Gemara says like this: וניבטליה בארבע
וניבטליה בחמש. V'nivatlei b'arba, v'nivatlei b'chameish.
So okay, we get why you have to do a ביטול, bittul,
but why when you do בדיקה bedika the night before, why not
do it the day of פסח, Pesach, which we know we do,
or the day of ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, which we know we
do when we burn it? The גמרא Gemara hasn't said that yet,
but it said, why do it the night before? Do it in
the fourth hour, the fifth hour? So the גמרא Gemara says no,
כיון דלאו זמן איסורא הוא ולאו זמן ביעורא הוא, Kiven d'lav zman
issura hu v'lav zman biyura hu, it's not a time of איסור,
issur, it's not yet the, you know, the 12th hour, the sixth
hour when it's אסור, assur, which is a clearly defined point where
people know hands off and it's not the time and it's not
the time
of destroying it, דילמא פשע ולא מבטל ליה. Dilma pasha v'lo mivatel
lei. So you'll be negligent, right? I mean חז"ל, Chazal, you know,
knew human psychology very well. If you connect it to the ritual
of בדיקת חמץ, bedikas chametz, you'll come to do it. If you
say you do it when you burn your חמץ, chametz, then you
won't come to do it. Look, I don't put out the 10
pieces and so on because I figure, you know, it's always what
happens when you put out the 10 and find nine, which the
גמרא Gemara is actually going to get to nonetheless. Right. So, you
know, I just do a בדיקה, bedika, and if I don't find
anything, I don't find anything. But then since I don't do any
שריפת חמץ srifas chametz in the next morning because I didn't have
anything, you know, it's harder for me to remember to do the
ביטול. bittul. Right? I try to do it first thing in the
morning, but if you don't have a ritual to assign it to
and you don't have a very specific time, you might come not
to do it.
We do actually do a ביטול bittul though
the night before, but we do a second one. I'm saying I
sometimes it, I don't forget, but I have to force myself, you
know, to focus and remember to do the second ביטול bittul because
I'm not doing a שריפת חמץ. srifas chametz.
No, the point in the גמרא, Gemara, it says: וניבטליה בארבע, V'nivatlei
b'arba, we actually do a...
I know, we haven't said that yet. So now the גמרא Gemara
top of ז' עמוד א', Zayin Amud Aleph, וניבטליה בשש, V'nivatlei b'sheish,
why not? How about the sixth hour? Meaning the, meaning the, it's
the 11:00. It's the beginning of the sixth hour. חמץ Chametz is
אסור assur at 12:00, I'm assuming a perfect day, sunrise at 6:00
and sunset at 6:00. So 12:00 is midday, but by 11:00 already
it's rabbinically אסור. assur. So since it's already rabbinically אסור assur and
everybody knows hands off, that moment has significance, that would be the
moment we would do ביטול. bittul. And presumably the גמרא Gemara is
saying, I get why you can't do it at 12:00, because then
as we said it's too late to do ביטול, bittul, it's already
not yours. But do it at 11:00 when it's only rabbinically אסור.
assur. So the גמרא Gemara says no, כיון דאיסורא דרבנן אית ליה,
Keivan d'issura d'rabbanan ilei, since it's rabbinically forbidden,
כדאורייתא דמיא, k'd'oraisa damya, it's like the biblical prohibition in the sense
of that you are no longer in a position to be מבטל
mevatel it. So this gets into an interesting question of the status
of איסורי הנאה דרבנן. issurei hana'ah d'rabbanan. Are things that are אסור
בהנאה דרבנן, assur b'hana'ah d'rabbanan, are they considered even for דאורייתא d'oraisa
purposes not yours? So let's take a look. And the very... so
גמרא Gemara says: ולאו ברשותיה קיימא, V'lav birshutei kayma, since it's rabbinically
forbidden, it's the same point, it's not in your רשות, reshus,
ולא מצי מבטל ליה, v'lo matzi mivatel lei, and you can't be
מבטל mevatel it. דאמר רב גידל אמר רב חייא בר יוסף אמר
רב המקדש משש שעות ולמעלה אפילו בחיטי קורדנייתא אין חוששין לקידושין. D'amar
Rav Gidel amar Rav Chiya bar Yosef amar Rav hamikadesh misheish sha'os
u'l'ma'la afilu b'chitei kordneisa ein chosheshin l'kidushin. If you a
מקדש, mekadesh, not a מקדיש. makdish. If you marry a woman with...
with...
grains of wheat from six hours onwards. Now רש"י Rashi says six
hours means even at 11:00, but that's not פשט. pshat. פשט Pshat
is at 12:00. It's the דאורייתא d'oraisa time, but it's חיטי קורדנייתא.
chitei kordneisa. Those are wheat grains that come from a certain place
and they're very hard and even if water gets on them, they
would never become, they would not really
ferment, they'd only be rabbinically חמץ. chametz. So he's saying if you
marry this woman with your wheat grains, which are rabbinically חמץ, chametz,
and it's already 12:00 onwards, אין חוששין לקידושין, ein chosheshin l'kidushin, then
there is no concern for קידושין, kidushin, there's not even a rabbinical
concern, she's totally not מקודשת. mekudeshes. They were אסור בהנאה assur b'hana'ah
and she's not מקודשת, mekudeshes, even though they were only rabbinically אסור
assur because it was only חמץ נוקשה. chametz nuksha. So the analogy
is the same way there it's biblical time period but rabbinical חמץ,
chametz, the same would be true with biblical חמץ chametz and a
rabbinical time period. So if it was real חמץ chametz at 11:00,
also it would effectively be considered not yours or worthless and therefore
it would not be a good קידושין. kidushin. Okay, and that raises
interesting questions about the rabbinic ability to change דאורייתא d'oraisa statuses. Because
you could say, they're not directly saying yes, דאורייתא d'oraisa she's married
because it really isn't אסור בהנאה assur b'hana'ah but we're going to
intervene. They could say in practice, since you're not able to derive
benefit within the culture in which we live because we've made it
forbidden to you rabbinically, so if in practice you're not able to
derive benefit, then it's worthless and therefore it doesn't matter whether it's
rabbinically that reason or biblically. I'll give you an analogy. Somebody who
is אסור assur to be as an עד מדרבנן. eid mid'rabbanan. If
he was an עד eid not מדאורייתא, mid'oraisa, only rabbinically אסור assur
as an עד. eid. And he was an עד קידושין. eid kidushin.
Is it a good קידושין? kidushin? Do you say דאורייתא d'oraisa yes
because he's a כשר kosher עד, eid, or do you say since
in practice he would never be accepted in court because we live
within a rabbinic culture, then even דאורייתא d'oraisa it's not a good
קידושין? kidushin? Okay, and that's debated. So it's a similar issue here
where the גמרא Gemara is saying is from 11:00 once it's rabbinically
forbidden then you cannot do ביטול bittul anymore anyway, it's effectively out
of your רשות reshus and the same way you can't do ביטול
bittul at 12:00, you can't do ביטול bittul at 11:00. Yes.
One could say this proves the opposite because it says משש שעות
ולמעלה. misheish sha'os u'l'ma'la. The גמרא Gemara is talking about, right,
so that's what I said. So רש"י Rashi tries to say that...
שש שעות ולמעלה shesh sha'os u'lema'alah means 11 o'clock onwards, the beginning
of שש. shesh. Almost all the ראשונים Rishonim disagree, they say שש
שעות ולמעלה shesh sha'os u'lema'alah always means 12 o'clock onwards, midday onwards,
but they say it's an analogy, it's חיטי קורדיינוס. chitei kordinos. חיטי
קורדיינוס Chitei kordinos is rabbinic חמץ. chametz. So the analogy is: rabbinic
חמץ chametz at the biblical time period would be, is analogous to,
biblical חמץ chametz at the rabbinic time period. But you understand what's
motivating רש"י Rashi to say שש שעות shesh sha'os means 11 o'clock.
Have I gone on for more than 18 minutes?
Yeah. Yeah. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says, so that's why
we couldn't do it that. So the גמרא Gemara says ולבתר איסורא
לא מצי מבטיל ליה u'lebatar issura lo matzi mevatil leh and therefore
once it's 11 o'clock you can't be מבטל mevatel anymore. So the
גמרא Gemara says והתניא, ve-hatanya, but we taught in a ברייתא, braita,
היושב בבית המדרש ונזכר שיש חמץ בתוך ביתו, ha-yoshev be-veis ha-midrash ve-nizkar
she-yesh chametz be-soch beiso,
if you're sitting in the בית מדרש beis midrash and you realize
you have חמץ chametz in your house—this is like the משנה mishnah
I told you, the one משנה mishnah that mentions you're going to
bring a קרבן פסח korban pesach and you remember you forgot to
do בדיקה. bedikah. So here it's talking you're sitting in the בית
מדרש beis midrash and you remembered you have חמץ chametz in your
house. מבטלו בלבו. mevatlo be-libo. Just do ביטול, bitul, you don't have
to get up from your דף יומי, daf yomi, just do ביטול
bitul and keep on learning. אחד שבת ואחד יום טוב, echad shabbos
ve-echad yom tov, whether it's שבת shabbos or יום טוב. yom tov.
So the גמרא Gemara says, what? What does that mean? בשלמא שבת,
bishlama shabbos, I get the שבת shabbos case. משכחת לה
כגון שחל ארבעה עשר להיות בשבת, meshachachas lah kegon she-chal arba'ah asar
lihyos be-shabbos, that it's when שבת shabbos fell on ערב פסח. erev
pesach. אלא יום טוב, ela yom tov, but if it's יום טוב,
yom tov, so it's פסח! pesach! So בתר איסורא הוא, batar issura
hu, it's after the איסור issur time! So we're no longer asking
why don't do the ביטול bitul earlier, we're questioning the very assumption,
why not do the ביטול bitul later? We said do the בדיקה
bedikah at night, why not later? It's too late. So we're questioning
the assumption, it's clearly not too late, clearly from this ברייתא braita
you see you can do ביטול bitul even after it's already פסח.
pesach. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא יום טוב בתר איסורא הוא?
ela yom tov batar issura hu? אמר רב אחא בר יעקב הכא
בעיסות היושב לפני רבו עסקינן. amar rav acha bar yaakov hacha be-issos
ha-yoshev lifnei rabbo askinan. No, it's
not,
here's the case. You're right, it is יום טוב, yom tov, but
here's why you can do ביטול. bitul. You're there, you're not just
סתם stam in the בית מדרש, beis midrash, you're in front of
your רבי. rebbe. ונזכר שיש עיסות מגלגלות בתוך ביתו, ve-nizkar she-yesh issos
megulgalos be-soch beiso, and you remembered that you left at home some
dough that you forgot to put in the oven. On יום טוב
yom tov you could have put it in the oven. That must
have been a very short trip from your house to the בית
מדרש beis midrash and you're there and you're sitting in front of
the רבי. rebbe. Maybe you walked right into שיעור shiur and then
you remembered, oh my god, I just left the dough, I didn't
put it in the oven. ומיתיירא שמא תחמיץ, u-misyara shema tachmitz,
so you're afraid it'll become חמץ, chametz, but it's not yet חמץ.
chametz. And that's why you can do ביטול, bitul, because it's not
yet חמץ. chametz. Yes, it's יום טוב, yom tov, but it's not
yet חמץ. chametz.
So קודם הוא ומבטלה מקמי דתחמיץ, kodem hu u-mevatlah mikamei de-tachmitz, so
then you can do ביטול bitul before it becomes חמץ, chametz, and
that's why you're allowed. So the גמרא Gemara says דיקא נמי דקתני,
dika nami de-kasani, that also can be inferred because it says היושב
בתוך בית המדרש. ha-yoshev be-soch beis ha-midrash.
If you were sitting in the בית המדרש. beis ha-midrash. Why does
it say היושב? ha-yoshev? Why the example of בית מדרש? beis midrash?
Or maybe why did it say היושב? ha-yoshev? Maybe היושב ha-yoshev suggests
this idea of the special circumstances that you're sitting in front of
your רבי rebbe and therefore you're not able to leave, and if
you, but meaning, if you were able to leave, you would have
presumably been able to have solved the problem. Now of course the
simple sense is, yeah, you would have solved the problem because you
would have gone home and destroyed it. Okay, but put it in
the oven, no, that's the גמרא's Gemara proof. The גמרא's Gemara proof
that we're talking about something that's not yet חמץ. chametz. Okay, but
it's a question of how big of a proof is it? Maybe
it was something that really is חמץ, chametz, but if you weren't
in the בית מדרש beis midrash you would have gone home and
destroyed it. Right, that's the question we had before, can you actually
actively destroy חמץ chametz on פסח, pesach, whether it has to be
בשרפה, be-sereifah, those types of questions. But the גמרא Gemara is saying
it sounds like there was a solution, and we assume the solution
would have been you would have prevented it from having become חמץ.
chametz. שמע מינה, shema mina, that is a good inference. So according
to the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא's Gemara introduced this idea which is
not in the משנה, mishnah, I repeat, that every time there is
בדיקה bedikah there is ביטול. bitul. You have a belt and suspenders.
And the reason you need the suspenders is because maybe you'll have
missed something. And then the emphasis all of a sudden shifts away
from the משנה mishnah which only talked about בדיקה, bedikah, only had
ביטול bitul as a last minute fallback.
And now it's all about this high focus on ביטול. bitul. When
you do the ביטול, bitul, you do when you do the בדיקה,
bedikah, when can you do it? You can't do it once it's
already אסור, assur, you can't do even when it's אסור דרבנן, assur
de-rabbanan, and even dealing with this ברייתא braita here that suggests you
can do it after פסח pesach and saying that no, that was
a case where it was not yet חמץ. chametz.
And so we're not worried that who's going to come back and
look so nice and they'll say who's this, this looks like a
really nice dough and it's חמץ chametz and דעתיה עליה? da'ateih aleih?
No. So there are some times where they allowed you to rely
on ביטול בעלמא. bitul be-alma. Those are special exceptions, that's true. But
not as a general rule. Okay, yeah.
When you're מבטל בלבו, mevatel be-libo, do you have to say something
out loud?
So we have, the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that. We've turned again,
we've ritualized it more and turned it into this very particular text.
Is it just your thought?
Yeah, exactly. And that gets to the question: what is it? Is
it הפקר? hefker? Are you doing an act of being מפקיר? mafkir?
That would more require something to be articulated. Is it just sort
of you're pulling your hands back? That could just be your state
of mind. But we've ritualized it as we've ritualized at the time
of the בדיקה bedikah and that helps us make sure we do
it at least, but you're right, the גמרא Gemara says בלבו, be-libo,
you're absolutely correct. Correct. Okay, so continuing in the דף, daf, אמר
רבה בר רב הונא אמר רב הפח שאיפש. amar rabbah bar rav
huna amar rav ha-pach she-ipash. Now we're actually going to switch the
conversation a little bit. You find bread in the bread basket, and
it's all moldy. כיון שרובה מצה, keivan she'rubah matzah, if you've used
this breadbasket, the majority of usage has been for מצה, matzah, that's
what the גמרא Gemara thinks it means. מותרת, Muteres, it's okay because
basically the point is you don't know whether it's bread or מצה.
matzah. Now, of course, we're not assuming the wafer-like cracker מצה, matzah,
we're assuming more like ספרדי Sefardi מצה, matzah, which is basically like
a pita, okay? So you've got this moldy thing and how the
heck do you know at this stage whether it was that pita
מצה matzah or whether it was the real bread? So it says
pita pita, so it says you can go by רוב, rov, so
it's pretty amazing, who the heck would ever consider going by רוב
rov even if technically you're allowed on פסח, Pesach, you know, the
end would be just throw it away. But the גמרא Gemara says
it's מותר. muttar. So the גמרא Gemara says you what?
You can eat the bread.
Moldy bread. You can eat the moldy bread, yeah, or you can
feed it to your dog or you can get הנאה hana'ah from
it. So feed it to your dog, you get הנאה hana'ah from
it, whatever you want to do with it, you can. היכי דמי,
Heichi dami, what's the case?
By the way, the word for potentially being מצה matzah here is
פת. pas.
Right, that's a good point to make. Right, it's the use of
פת pas and yet who would have thought to say פת pas
by, you know, I mean look, the תורה, Torah, מצה matzah is
like לחם lechem also, you know, so right, exactly. Okay. היכי דמי,
Heichi dami, what's the case? אילימא דידע ביה דחמץ היא, Ilima deyada
beih dechametz hi, if you know it's חמץ, chametz, כי רוב מצה
מאי הוי, ki rov matzah mai havi, who cares what you mostly
use the basket for? אלא דלא ידעינן אי חמץ הוא אי מצה,
Ella dila yadinan ei chametz hu ei matzah, you don't know if
it was חמץ chametz or מצה. matzah. מאי איריא כי רוב מצה,
Mai irya ki rov matzah, so who cares that most of the
time you use מצה? matzah? That should not be the determinant. What
should be the determinant? אפילו כי לא רוב מצה נמי ניזיל בתר
בתרא, Afilu ki lo rov matzah nami neizil basar basra, you thought
the גמרא Gemara was going to be more מחמיר. machmir. No, אפילו
כי לא רוב מצה נמי ניזיל בתר בתרא, afilu ki lo rov
matzah nami neizil basar basra, even if the majority isn't מצה, matzah,
we should go by the last use. So if it's already let's
say פסח, Pesach, and we would say, you know, or I don't
know, you're getting ready for פסח, Pesach, and we would say, what
was the last thing you remember using the basket for? The last
thing I remember using the basket was for my מצה, matzah, then
we should be able to assume מצה matzah even if most of
the time, who cares most of the time? What we care is
in the immediate, you know, past, what was the most recent thing
that you can remember using it for? מי לא תנן, Mi lo
tnan, did we not teach in a משנה? Mishnah? מעות שנמצאו לפני
סוחרי בהמה, Ma'os shenimtze'u lifnei sochrei behema, there's you find money in
front of people that sell animals, you know, for slaughter, in
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. לעולם מעשר, Le'olam ma'aser, you have to assume no matter
what time of the year it is that it's מעשר ma'aser money
because most people, you'd have all this tons of מעשר שני ma'aser
sheni money. Of course you have to think about that מעשר, ma'aser,
you know, I mean what happens if it's not a מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni year? But okay, you have tons of מעשר שני ma'aser
sheni money for, you know, a tenth of all the produce you
grew, you're living out somewhere in אשקלון Ashkelon or something, and you
can't schlep all the produce, so you take like $5,000 of מעשר
שני ma'aser sheni money with you to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. When do you
take it? You take it when you're עולה לרגל. oleh laregel. How
much food can you eat in the רגל? regel? So what are
you going to do? So רש"י Rashi says, you want basically just
like, you know, give it to the עניים aniyim or something, or
you give it to people who live in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and the
most and they have to use it for food, and a common
thing they would use it for would be meat. Maybe it would
be also a good way to spend a lot of money with,
you know, in a short period of time. But also because רש"י
Rashi says it's seen as appropriate to use your מעשר ma'aser money
to bring a שלמים, Shelamim, to bring a קרבן שלמים. korban Shelamim.
Okay? So therefore, moneys that are found in the area of the
butchers in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, most
no matter what time of year it is, it generally is מעשר
ma'aser money. And if you assume and if you find it, you
have to treat it as מעשר ma'aser money. בהר הבית, Behar Habayis,
now let's say you find it on the Temple Mount itself, okay?
People aren't going there buying animals, they so חולין, chulin, then you
don't have to assume that it's מעשר ma'aser money, it's just normal
money. Normal money is most likely it's חולין. chulin. Of course, now
רש"י, Rashi, תוספות Tosafos says no no no, no, it's on the
place where you would go up to the בית. bayis. So תוספות
Tosafos says, I thought you weren't allowed to go up to הר
הבית Har Habayis with your wallet, you know, so תוספות Tosafos says
maybe that only means in public, maybe because it looks like you're
going like, you know, to the marketplace, but doesn't mean you can't
have money in your pocket. Okay.
בירושלים, Biyerushalayim, now if you found the money in the streets of
ירושלים Yerushalayim itself, so
בשעת הרגל, beshas haregel, if it's during the time of the רגל,
regel, מעשר. ma'aser. Then it's מעשר ma'aser because, you know, it's not
in front of the people that are selling the animals. On the
other hand, everybody has been עולה לרגל oleh laregel and a major
thing that they bring with them is money to spend is their
מעשר ma'aser money. So a majority of money that's around ירושלים Yerushalayim
at the time of the רגל regel is מעשר ma'aser money. בשאר
ימות השנה חולין, Bish'ar yemos hashanah chulin, but anytime not the רגל,
regel, it's considered to be חולין. chulin. Now the question is, why
is that? Why don't we assume that even at the rest of
the time of the year maybe it was leftover מעשר ma'aser money,
especially it's I don't know, like a day after the רגל, regel,
two days after the רגל, regel, why don't we assume that the
majority of money that still, you know, might have fallen on the
ground, you know, mostly is מעשר ma'aser money? ואמר רב שמיה בר
זירא מאי טעמא, Ve'amar Rav Shmaya bar Zeira mai ta'ama, what is
the reason we say this? הואיל ושוקי ירושלים עשוין להתכבד בכל יום,
Ho'il veshukei Yerushalayim asuyin lehiskaibed bechol yom, because they sweep the marketplaces
on a daily basis. So we thought it was only in New
York they had daily street cleaning, you have to move your car
every day. Okay.
So in ירושלים Yerushalayim too, they would sweep every day. And therefore
we can assume that the money you would find would be from
the most recent. even if it was just a day after the
רגל, regel, we can assume that it is money that you would
find, that is money that fell within the last day. So of
course the question is is that, you know, that's because they swept
it every day. It's not necessarily saying you cleaned out your bread
basket every day. It's not exactly in the same analogy. But anyway,
the גמרא Gemara says like this, אלמא אמרינן, alma amrinan, so you
see you say קמאי קמאי אזלו ליה, kamai kamai azlu leh, that
the first stuff has gone away, והני אחריני נינהו, vehanei achrinei ninhu,
and this is new stuff. So הכא נמי נימא, hacha nami neima,
so let's say here too קמאי קמאי אזלו, kamai kamai azlu, the
first stuff no longer was here. Even if you use it for
bread in the previous weeks and that was the majority, that's no
longer what your recent use has been. והאי
דהאידנא היא, vehay dehaidna hi, and this is of nowadays, meaning it's
of, you know, if it's on פסח Pesach or it's, you know,
so most recently you've been using it for מצה. matzah. So the
גמרא Gemara says, לא, שאני הכא דאיפושא מוכח עילויה. lo, shani hacha
de'ipusha mochach iluyei. No, no, no, here you can't go by recent
because it's moldy. So if it's moldy, then it's clearly not from
the last few days. So the גמרא Gemara says, אי איפושא מוכח
עילויה, ei ipusha mochach iluyei, if the mold is such a good
evidence that it's from way back, כי ריבסא דמצה מאי הוי, ki
rivsa dematzah mai havei, who cares if the majority of time you've
used מצה, matzah, you know, maybe it's some, you know, so meaning
maybe because part of that majority has to do with your recent
usage, you know, it's clearly from a previous time and a time
when you were using it for חמץ. chametz. So the גמרא Gemara
says, so מאי הוי, mai havei, so אמר רבא, amar Rava, לא
תימא שריבסא דמצה, lo teima sherivsa dematzah, fine, it doesn't mean the
majority of usage was מצה, matzah, אלא אימא שרבו ימי מצה עילויה.
ela eima sherabu yemei matzah iluyei. It means most of פסח Pesach
has passed. So even if it's moldy, you can by the combination
of assuming it's probably recent usage and the mold is probably because
it's, you know, from the beginning of פסח, Pesach, so then you're
safe. אי הכי פשיטא, ei hachi peshita, then it's obvious. לא, צריכא
דאיפושא מרובה, lo, tzericha de'ipusha meruba, that's very moldy. מהו דתימא, mahu
deteima, I might have thought, כיון דאיפושא מרובה איגלאי מילתא דודאי חמץ
מעליא הוא, keivan de'ipusha meruba iglai milta devadai chametz mealya hu, since
it's very moldy, it clearly came from the time
before פסח Pesach began and it's חמץ. chametz. קא משמע לן, ka
mashma lan, we say, it teaches us, כיון שרבו ימי מצה עילויה,
keivan sherabu yemei matzah iluyei, since most of פסח Pesach has passed,
אמרינן כל יומא ויומא נמי חמימי אפו, amrinan kol yoma veyoma nami
chamimei afu, how did it get so moldy? So because every day
you were baking fresh bread. Look at that, right? We, God forbid,
you know, we should, you know, put any water to any flour
on פסח Pesach itself, right? But here, no, why? You just bake
it מצה, matzah, you don't bake it חמץ. chametz. So every day
you're baking fresh bread on פסח, Pesach, fresh מצה, matzah, אפו ושדו
עילויה, afu veshadu iluyei, and you threw the fresh bread on this
tiny little thing that was at the bottom of the bread basket,
ואפשא טפי, ve'afsha tefai, and that caused it to get more moldy.
Okay, but what's the problem? The תשביתו חמץ, tashbitu chametz, it's אינו
ראוי למאכל כלב, eino ra'uy lema'achal kelev, and it's so moldy.
It says it's not that moldy.
So there's parts of it, it's רבו איפושה, rubo ipushei, it's very
moldy.
All right. So there are parts that are still not, you know,
it's like the debate that my wife and I have, right? You
find some moldy thing, I say, okay, well you can still salvage
this piece of it.
Throw the whole thing of cheddar cheese out, you don't just cut
it off.
Right, that's what you do? If some of your cheese is moldy,
you cut off, you salvage what you can salvage.
Okay, so with the authorization of your wife.
Okay, so we can go around and have a little poll here.
But anyway, this something is ראוי לאכילה. ra'uy la'achila. Anyway, the חידוש
chiddush of the גמרא Gemara is very interesting. First of all, that
clearly their מצה matzah did not look anything like our מצה, matzah,
looked much more like פת. pas. But also, you know, it did
not have problems assuming that you can go by normal principles of
רוב rov or this principle of by the most recent use if
that's the good way of determining it and just go ahead and
eat something that we would sort of say, you know, oh my
god, if there's a slight possibility it's חמץ chametz of course you
got to just throw it out. So that's not the sort of
at least where it starts within the גמרא. Gemara.
Well if it looks the same as the bread then you have
to assume that because if you wake up in the morning and
there's pizza in your basket it's because it's פסח, Pesach, it wouldn't
have been חמץ, chametz, of course.
Right, right. So I mean if you actually do if that's type
of assumption you can make, right? That you which is sort of
the גמרא's Gemara idea of אזלינן בתר בתרא. azlinan batar batra. It's
like, of course, I cleaned out the whole house, what else would
it be? Right, right. So yeah, but yeah, but I think the
what which is but then the גמרא Gemara sort of says that
פשיטא, peshita, you know, in certain cases, right? But yes, but the
גמרא Gemara I think is willing to do that reliance even if
you're not certain, even if it's just that you can rely on
that, you know, that method even without being certain. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, ומי אזלינן בתר בתרא, umi azlinan
batar batra, is it really true you go by the most recent?
That's a way of determining the identity? והתניא רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
אומר, vehatanya Rabbi Yossi berabi Yehuda omer, Rabbi Yossi berabi Yehuda says,
תיבה שנשתמשו בה מעות חולין, teiva shenishtamshu ba ma'os chullin, so again
we're no longer in פסח. Pesach. You have a box, your money
box. So if you use it both for חולין chullin money, non-sanctified
money, ומעות מעשר, uma'os ma'aser, and מעשר ma'aser money, and you found
a coin in it and you don't know what it is, אם
רוב חולין חולין, im rov chullin chullin, if mostly you use it
for חולין, chullin, then you can assume it's חולין. chullin. אם רוב
מעשר מעשר, im rov ma'aser ma'aser, and if mostly you use it
for מעשר, ma'aser, and we don't say what was your last use.
Right? This is a good example, right? You found something at the
bottom of your money box, you know most recently you used it
for מעשר, ma'aser, but you don't know that it fell from the
most recent money you put in. Maybe it fell from a week
ago. Do you go by its most recent use or its most
common use? Very, very good question. You know, you could see going
either way. And this says you go by the most common use.
ואמאי, ve'amai, why is that true? ליזיל בתר בתרא, leizil batar batra,
why don't we ask you what was the most recent thing you
used it for? אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק הכא במאי עסקינן, amar
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak hacha bemai askinan, what are we
talking
about? כגון שנשתמשו kegon shenishtamshu It's you
know, today you do this one, the next day you do that
one, and you forget what did I do it most recently? I
don't remember what I used it for most recently today. Oh, so
in that case you go by רוב rov when you don't know
what the most recent use is. Okay, the גמרא's Gemara now going
to have two other answers which are somewhat similar. Or רב זביד
Rav Zevid אמר amar כגון שנשתמשו בה ציבורין ציבורין. kegon she-nishtamshu bah
tziburin tziburin. You actually used it for both at the same time.
You put—but how could you mix מעשר ma'aser and חולין chullin money?
So fine, you put מעשר ma'aser money, you know, in one little
pouch in the box here and the חולין chullin money in another
little pouch. But you use it for both at the same time.
And therefore you don't—so in that case you would go by רוב.
rov. רב פפא Rav Pappa אמר amar כגון דאשתכח בגומא. kegon de-ishtakach
be-guma. No, you found it in a little crevice in the box.
So clearly even when you emptied the box from its previous usage,
you would have missed that coin. So clearly it would not have,
you know, there's no reason to assume it fell from the most
recent usage. The reason you go by the most recent is you
assume you empty it from one usage and you use it all
new from another one, but this stuff would have escaped the emptying
and therefore you can't go by recent, you have to go by
רוב. rov. Okay, so that was an interesting little digression which really
had nothing to do with our discussions of בדיקה bedika and ביטול,
bitul, I must say. I don't even know what it's doing here.
Was it the same תנא? tanna? Was it—it was רבה בר רב
הונא אמר רב. Rabbah bar Rav Huna amar Rav. We didn't have
רבה בר רב הונא אמר רב Rabbah bar Rav Huna amar Rav
before, did we? I really don't know what that was doing here.
Maybe because of—has to do with the types of assumptions that you're
allowed to make.
Right, well that's what I'm saying. The way you're allowed to use
normal, you know, decision-making principles in—right,
by פסח Pesach we have just assumed such a taboo that it
would never occur to us, you know, well, majority, so probably. All
right, let's now take a look. Anyway, I don't know exactly what
that was doing here. But now we get back to statements of
רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, רב יהודה אמר רב Rav Yehuda amar Rav
about בדיקה bedika and ביטול. bitul. So
אמר
רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, הבודק צריך שיברך. Ha-bodek tzarich she-yivarech. If
you do בדיקה, bedika, you have to make a ברכה. bracha. So
now we're ritualizing the בדיקה, bedika, right? דוב Dov before pointed out
we've ritualized the ביטול, bitul, we now make it a formal statement
that we say out loud, you know. First of all we make
it a requirement that we make it a formal statement. We're also
going to ritualize the בדיקה. bedika. You know, the משנה, Mishna, you
know, speaks about בודקין לאור הנר bodkin le-or ha-ner and so, but
it doesn't necessarily mean it's a ritual. It's just saying you check
and it's telling you use candlelight because we'll see, you know, that's
the best way to find things in the cracks and crevices. But
the גמרא, Gemara, it now becomes a ritual of בדיקה bedika and
therefore there's a ברכה bracha that you make for it. Okay, so
צריך שיברך, tzarich she-yivarech, that's already a חידוש. chiddush. מאי מברך, Mai
mivarech, what ברכה bracha do you make? רב פפי Rav Pappi אמר
amar משמיה דרבא, mishmei de-Rava, so רב פפי Rav Pappi says in
the name of רבא, Rava, לבער חמץ. le-va'er chametz. You say אשר
קדשנו במצותיו וצונו לבער חמץ, Asher kiddishanu be-mitzvotav ve-tzivanu le-va'er chametz, destroy
חמץ, chametz, because this is a part of the process of the
דאורייתא מצוה De-Oraita mitzvah of ביעור חמץ bi'ur chametz of, you know,
תשביתו שאור. tashbitu se'or. You מבער, miva'er, you first find it and
then you destroy it. רב פפא Rav Pappa אמר amar משמיה דרבא,
mishmei de-Rava, על ביעור חמץ. al bi'ur chametz. So he agrees that
conceptually it's about an act of ביעור חמץ, bi'ur chametz, of destroying
חמץ, chametz, but rather than לבער, le-va'er, to destroy, he says על
ביעור חמץ, al bi'ur chametz, on the destroying of חמץ. chametz. So
now what's this debate about? So let's take a look. בלבער, Be-le-va'er,
regarding the use of the phrase לבער, le-va'er, to destroy חמץ, chametz,
כולי עלמא לא פליגי דודאי להבא משמע. kulei alma lo peligi de-vadai
le-haba mashma. That certainly means that you're going to do it now
in the future, you know, immediately now. להבא Le-haba is later. Right,
but I mean, but coming up, you're going to do it in
the future, not the distant future. I'm going to do it in
a minute from now. On לבער, le-va'er, to destroy חמץ chametz which
I am about to do.
כי פליגי בעל ביעור. Ki peligi be-al bi'ur. The question is on
the burning of חמץ. chametz. מר סבר מעיקרא משמע. Mar savar me-ikara
mashma. One says you can't say על ביעור חמץ. al bi'ur chametz.
על Al means on the thing that already happened. You commanded us
on the burning, on the destroying of חמץ chametz implies that we
already did, not to do something in the future, but on the
thing that happened. And therefore you can't use an על al phrase.
ומר סבר להבא משמע. U-mar savar le-haba mashma. No, on the burning
of חמץ chametz can still mean that we're about to do and
it can mean to the future.
Then why don't we just say לבער le-va'er then, if according
to—well, I'll discuss that in a minute. Okay. So the גמרא's Gemara
now going to go to discussions about when do we say על
ביעור חמץ, al bi'ur chametz, an על al phrase, to prove that
על al can mean the future. Okay, so let's take a look.
מיתיבי, Meitivi, I'll ask you on this: ברוך אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו
על המילה, Baruch asher kiddishanu be-mitzvotav ve-tzivanu al ha-mila, on the מילה,
mila, which is—so that's a standard ברכת המצוה, birchas ha-mitzvah, it's intended
for the future and you say על המילה. al ha-mila. The גמרא
Gemara says התם היכא נימא. Hatam hacha nima. No, no, no. You
can't say the ל. le. What do you want the guy to
say there? נימא למול, Nima la-mul, to do a מילה? mila? לא
סגי דלאו איהו מהיל? Lo sagi delao ihu mahil? What, he's the
one that was commanded to do the מילה? mila? No, he's the
מוהל. mohel. The father's commanded to do. When you say you commanded
us למול, la-mul, it means commanded me to do this מילה. mila.
That's not true. But you say you commanded us על מילה al
mila means not that I personally have the obligation,
we— Even
if you're the one doing the מילה. Mila.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אבי הבן מאי קאמרי, Avi ha-ben mai
ka'amre, so if the father does the מילה, Mila, so then what
would you say? אי הכי נמי, Inami, sure, then let him say
למול, l'mol, no problem. Now you're going to say we always say
על המילה. al ha-mila. We'll get back to that.
Okay, now, so that's answer number...
what?
And I did my son's ברית מילה. Brit Mila. And what'd you
say? I'm just from trying to remember. No, you do at least
אשכנזים Ashkenazim always do על המילה. al ha-mila. So maybe ספרדים Sefardim
don't... I'll get to that in a minute. But anyway, so תוספות
Tosfos points out, by the way, that if we can acknowledge that
sometimes על al works when there's a need to say על, al,
then clearly everybody admits that על al can suggest the future, right?
Because if it could only suggest the past, we would never have
allowed it. But nevertheless, the ל le says, it's much more suggesting
the past than the future. I'll use it when I need to,
but when I don't need to I'm going to use ל. le.
Okay? So now we're going to take other examples where we use
על al and have to defend why those are cases that you
needed to use על. al. Let's take a look.
And appreciate this, still, at this time, ברכות brachot were flexible, you
could change the wording depending upon the circumstances.
Right, exactly. Not you as the individual, but like, but you know,
it doesn't mean you can choose. When the גמרא Gemara says אי
הכי נמי Inami it means fine, that'll be the הלכה. halacha. But
right, but that it would be different ברכות brachot for different people,
right, for different circumstances.
And then post-Tannaic.
I know, I know. I'll talk in a minute about what the
conclusion is. Okay, let's keep on going. The גמרא Gemara says like
this: מיתיבי, Meisvei,
ברוך אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על השחיטה. Baruch asher kidishanu b'mitzvotav v'tzivanu
al ha-shechita. So again it's על, al, which the שוחט shohet says,
התם נמי, hasham nami, היכי נימא, heichi neima, what do you want
him to say? נימא לשחוט, Neima lishchot, to שחט? shecht? means I
am commanded to שחט. shecht. What? לא סגי דלאו איהו שחיט, lo
sagi d'lav ish shachit, it's not sufficient that he not him to
do שחיטה, shechita, meaning what, he's only he can do the שחיטה?
shechita? No. So therefore על השחיטה al ha-shechita is much more abstract
and general because he is not particularly commanded. So says פסח וקדשים
מאי קאמרי? Pesach v'kadshim mai ka'amrei? What about a guy bringing a
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach or bringing a קרבן Korban where there's an
idea that at least ideally even though often the כהנים Kohanim and
others would שחט, shecht, but you know, he could, you know, if
he did it, he actually would be commanded to שחט shecht although
he could sort of, you know, sort of
hand that off, like by the מילה. Mila. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אי הכי נמי, Inami, sure, you know, let him go ahead
and do it, say לשחוט lishchot if he's actually commanded. Okay so
again we have the possibility that it would differ based on circumstances.
מיתיבי, Meisvei, the גמרא Gemara says I'll ask you on this: העושה
לולב לעצמו מברך, Ha'oseh lulav l'atzmo mevarech, if you make a לולב,
lulav, when you're making it even ערב סוכות erev Succot you say
שהחיינו וקימנו והגיענו לזמן הזה. shehecheyanu v'kiyamanu v'higianu lazman hazeh. So this
is an interesting thing. We make the ברכה bracha שהחיינו shehecheyanu when
we do מצוות mitzvot like holiday מצוות, mitzvot, יום טוב yom tov
מצוות, mitzvot, the first time we do them, sit in a סוכה,
succah, take the
לולב, lulav, you know, eat
מצה, matzah, blow שופר, shofar, right. So we do those, okay,
but הלכה halacha actually you don't have to do it at the
time of the מצוה. mitzvah. The שהחיינו shehecheyanu is because it's a
new מצוה mitzvah time period and as soon as you begin to
relate to the מצוה mitzvah you can make the ברכה bracha שהחיינו,
shehecheyanu, like you can make a ברכה bracha when you buy the
car or when you first drive it. So you can make the
ברכה bracha שהחיינו shehecheyanu when you're putting together your סוכה succah or
when you first sit in it. So according to you know, the
Tannaic level, it was always you do it when you're making it.
We now do it when we first do it. העושה לולב לעצמו
מברך שהחיינו וקימנו והגיענו לזמן הזה. Ha'oseh lulav l'atzmo mevarech shehecheyanu v'kiyamanu
v'higianu lazman hazeh. נטלו לצאת בו, Natlo latzet bo, when you take
it to be יוצא, yotzei, אומר אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על נטילת
לולב. omer asher kidishanu b'mitzvotav v'tzivanu al netilat lulav. Then you say
על נטילת. al netilat. Why do you say על? al? Why not
say ליטול? litol? So the גמרא Gemara says no, שאני התם, shani
hasham, there it's different, בעידנא דאגבהי נפיק ביה, d'idana d'agbei nafik bei,
because actually it is after the fact. When you're holding onto your
לולב lulav you're already יוצא. yotzei. Now we turn the אתרוג etrog
upside down. But the גמרא Gemara says, you know, actually sometimes you
wind up making it after you've already been יוצא, yotzei, so we
need to be על. al. אי הכי לצאת בו? Iy hachi latzet
bo? So then why does it say if you picked it up
to be יוצא? yotzei? יצא בו מיבעי ליה, Yatza bo mibayei, it
should have said when you picked it up and were יוצא. yotzei.
So it sounds like you haven't been יוצא yotzei yet. So the
גמרא Gemara says אי הכי נמי, Inami, yes, but that's what it
means, as soon as you pick it up you're יוצא. yotzei. So
why did it say לצאת? latzet? ומשום דקבעי למתני סיפא, umshum d'ka
ba'ei l'misni seifa, because it wants to say at the end, לישב
בסוכה, leishev basuccah, giving the scenario of when you sit in your
סוכה, succah, תנא רישא נמי לצאת בו. tana reisha nami latzet bo.
So here it says you took it to do the מצוה mitzvah
of לולב, lulav, but actually you've already done the מצוה. mitzvah. Now
where did it say it by סוכה? succah? דקתני סיפא, D'ktani seifa,
the end of that says...
that's a תוספתא tosefta that says, העושה סוכה לעצמו, ha'oseh succah l'atzmo,
when you're making your סוכה, succah, אומר omer you say ברוך אתה
ה' שהחיינו וקימנו והגיענו לזמן הזה. baruch atah Hashem shehecheyanu v'kiyamanu v'higianu
lazman hazeh. נכנס לישב בה, Nichnas leishev ba, when you first sit
in it, you say ברוך אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו לישב בסוכה. baruch
asher kidishanu b'mitzvotav v'tzivanu leishev basuccah. So since there it was prior,
לישב, leishev, we said לצאת latzet by the לולב, lulav, but actually
the לולב lulav you were already יוצא. yotzei. Now תוספות Tosfos says,
you can't really say 100% you were יוצא yotzei and you were
done with the מצוה mitzvah because then how could you still be
making a ברכת המצוה? birkas hamitzvah? So that gets into this idea
that you know, continuing to shake the לולב lulav or continuing to
hold it on after you've already picked it up is actually a
continuation of the מעשה מצוה. ma'aseh mitzvah. So technically you've been יוצא
yotzei but you're still in the מצוה. mitzvah. middle of the מצוה
mitzvah and therefore you're still doing it even though you've already been
יוצא yotzei and therefore you would make על al rather than ליטול
לולב. litol lulav. Okay, so basically we have the position that says
you always say ל le unless you have to say על, al,
and the other position that no, you say על. al. And what's
the הלכה? halacha? So the גמרא Gemara says, והלכתא על ביעור חמץ.
vehilchasa al biyur chametz. The הלכה halacha is we say על ביעור
חמץ. al biyur chametz. And because the גמרא Gemara says that על
al is not problematic in meaning future, you don't need to defend
it. It's not a problematic way of referring to the future. So
רש״י Rashi says now all of our distinctions go away. That's why
when you do מילה, milah, even if the father is doing it,
he would say על המילה, al hamilah, or when you do שחיטה,
shechitah, even if it's קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, you'd say על השחיטה,
al hashechitah,
because על, al, you don't need to have a particular need to
make it, you know, to say על. al. על al can mean
the future also and therefore we're not going to make distinctions based
on those cases. Of course the question that still remains is, okay,
I get that על al can non-problematically mean the future. But how
come still sometimes we say על al and sometimes we say ל?
le? So if you take a look at this תוספות Tosafos where
it says
he says, והלכתא
על ביעור חמץ,
vehilchasa al
biyur chametz, he says, יכול הוא לומר כן שאף זו הלשון משמע
להבא או שמא דוקא על ביעור חמץ. yachol hu lomar ken she'af
zu halashon mashma l'haba o shema davka al biyur chametz. So first
תוספות Tosafos doesn't know if it means you have to say על
ביעור חמץ al biyur chametz or you can say על ביעור חמץ.
al biyur chametz. Maybe we still have a דוקא והלכתא. davka vehilchasa.
So first תוספות Tosafos says maybe we have a preference for ל
le but we'll allow you to say על ביעור. al biyur. Or
maybe you have to say על. al. Then he says, ויש טעם
בברכות ורי לא מצא טעם לכל הברכות. veyesh taam b'brachos veRi lo
matza taam l'chol habrachos. So the ר״י Ri tried to figure out
how come some are על al and some are ל le and
he couldn't. There's a huge ר״ן Ran here that tries to go
through every single ברכת המצוה birchas hamitzvah we ever made and figure
out why do you say על al sometimes and ל le sometimes.
I will tell you that one key difference is, which the גמרא
Gemara already emphasized, how much it focuses on the act, me personally
being obligated, but I will also say whether it's act-focused or whether
it's result-focused. So for example, you know, על המילה al hamilah could
be because the ultimately it focuses on achieving an end result. על
ביעור חמץ al biyur chametz focuses on achieving an end result, having
there be no חמץ, chametz, right? Whereas some things, you know, well
it doesn't work for על נטילת לולב al netilas lulav but it
does work for לישב בסוכה, leyshev basukkah, להניח תפילין. lehaniach tefillin. Those
more have to do with the acts, not with some sort of
the act just being a means for creating some, you know, end
type of a result.
So that's one certainly difference between the ל le and the על,
al, if it's personal or general, and also if it's act-focused or
result-focused, but it is, there is not a clear answer why we
do it all the time. I will also point out an, I
mean why what the distinctions always are, what they're based on. I
will also point out that תוספות Tosafos makes an previous עמוד amud
has an interesting discussion about the ברכה bracha about
אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו, asher kideshanu bemitzvosav vetzivanu,
one minute,
oh, להכניסו בבריתו של אברהם אבינו. lehachniso bevriso shel Avraham Avinu. So
since you're saying להכניסו, lehachniso,
which is להבא משמע, l'haba mashma, he says you should say it
before the act of מילה. milah. And then he says, no, no,
no, no, the only things you have to say before are ברכת
המצוה. birchas hamitzvah. להכניסו בבריתו lehachniso bevriso is not a ברכת המצוה
birchas hamitzvah on the מילה, milah, it's a, I mean it's אשר
קדשנו asher kideshanu but it's not a ברכת המצוה birchas hamitzvah on
the מילה. milah. It's a more of a ברכת השבח birchas hashevach
that the father is making because that we as כלל ישראל Klal
Yisrael have been commanded and it's in response to the מילה, milah,
not prior to the מילה. milah. And therefore he says you actually,
even though it's ל, le, it's not a ברכת המצוה, birchas hamitzvah,
so it does not have to come before. And that also raises
interesting questions because the last line of that תוספות, Tosafos, maybe I
will ask you to turn back the page, he
says, ותדע שהרי ברכת אירוסין אינו מברך אלא אחר האירוסין. veseda sheharei
birchas eirusin eino mevarech ela achar haeirusin. Okay,
now I don't know how many weddings you've been to, but the
weddings I've been to, you make the ברכת אירוסין birchas eirusin before
the מסירת טבעת. mesiras tabaat. Okay, but there actually is a major
מחלוקת ראשונים machlokes Rishonim whether you make the ברכת אירוסין birchas eirusin
before, is it a ברכת המצוה, birchas hamitzvah, or do you make
it after, is it a ברכת השבח birchas hashevach responding to the
experience of the אירוסין eirusin and the fact that we did this
מצוה, mitzvah, we're giving שבח. shevach. Because if you think about it,
both, you know, it's not a, ברכת אירוסין birchas eirusin is not
a simple אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על הקידושין. asher kideshanu bemitzvosav vetzivanu
al hakiddushin. It's, you know, אסר לנו את העריות והתיר לנו את
הארוסות. asar lanu es ha'arayos vehitir lanu es ha'arusos. So it becomes
much more a ברכת השבח. birchas hashevach. So sometimes there are ברכות
brachos that could have the אשר קדשנו במצותיו asher kideshanu bemitzvosav sort
of formulation but they're still fundamentally ברכת השבח birchas hashevach connected to
the מצוה mitzvah and they come after, not before. So that's another
interesting thing to be thinking, and that could be a ל. le.
Okay, but in terms of ברכת המצוה, birchas hamitzvah, that's always before,
and the question when do we decide between ל le and על
al is not spelled out in the גמרא. Gemara. I can't, yeah
I can't take the question because no, it's not clearly better. There
might be reasons, like I said, על al might refer more to
end result. Also you don't personally have to do the בדיקה, bedikah,
somebody else could do the בדיקה bedikah for you. There are reasons.
Anyway, let's take a look now, I want to get at least
get to the two dots. The גמרא Gemara says like this. דכולי
עלמא מיהא, d'chulei alma miha, everybody nevertheless agrees, מעיקרא בעינן לברוכי, meikara
ba'inan livrucha, you have to make a ברכת המצוה birchas hamitzvah before
the מצוה. mitzvah. מנלן, Minalan, where do you know that? דאמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל. d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel. כל המצוות מברך עליהן
עובר לעשייתן, Kol hamitzvos mevarech aleihen over la'asiyasan, on all ברכת המצוות
birchas hamitzvos מצוות mitzvos the ברכה bracha comes before you do them.
So now, מאי משמע דהאי עובר לישנא דאקדומי הוא? Mai mashma d'hai
over lishna d'akdumei hu? How do you know עובר לעשייתן over la'asiyasan
means prior to doing it? Maybe it means after doing it? אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak סנת פוני, snat
poni, we're going to quote פסוקים psukim to explain a line from
רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, what עובר לעשייתן over
la'asiyasan means. So so you know דאמר קרא, d'amar kra, it's not
like like we're explaining another פסוק, pasuk, we're explaining רב יהודה אמר
שמואל Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel because the פסוק pasuk says וירץ אחימעץ
דרך הככר, vayaratz Achima'atz derech hakikar, so אחימעץ Achima'atz ran by the
way of the sort of valley, ויעבור את הכושי, vaya'avor es hakushi,
and he passed in front of the כושי. Kushi. So he says
of so he preceded passed in front, so we're understanding that to
mean it means to go in front of.
Although what he did is he left the כושי Kushi behind him,
so you could say that you know maybe the ברכה bracha leaves
the מצוה mitzvah behind. Anyway, אביי אמר מהכא, Abaye amar mehacha, והוא
עובר לפניהם, v'hu over lifnehem, עבר לפניהם, avar lifnehem, he passed in
front of them. ואי בעית אימא מהכא, V'iy ba'is eima mehacha, ויעבור
מלכם לפניהם והשם בראשם, vaya'avor malkam lifnehem v'Hashem berosham, their king went
in front of them, so it means to go in front of.
בי רב אמרי, Bei Rav amri, okay. So that's what you do
prior. Now why do you do it prior? So actually I want
to say because the ברכת המצוה birchas hamitzvah fundamentally is a to
frame the act of the מצוה. mitzvah. Sort of like there's a
whole discussion whether מצוות צריכות כוונה mitzvos tzrichos kavana or not, but
even but ברכת המצוה birchas hamitzvah almost alleviates that responsibility because you
are labeling this as where I'm about to do a מצוה. mitzvah.
And to label something and to frame it obviously it comes before,
and that's in contrast to what I just said afterwards that ברכת
השבח birchas hashevach comes afterwards because ברכת השבח birchas hashevach is responding
to the experience, not framing the experience. ברכת הנהנין Birchas hanehenin also
comes before because you have to acknowledge that you know that this
you know comes from God before you're allowed to get benefit. So
נהנין nehenin comes before to allow you to get benefit, מצוה mitzvah
comes before to frame it, שבח shevach comes after to respond to
it. And I just have to give this one example about the
ברכה bracha we make at הבדלה Havdalah about you know which is
בורא מאורי האש. Borei me'orei ha'eish. Where everybody says בורא מאורי האש
Borei me'orei ha'eish and then they look at it. But it's not
a ברכת הנהנין. birchas hanehenin. The גמרא Gemara says
עד שיאותו לאורו, ad sheye'osu l'oro, you first have to be נהנה.
nehena. בורא מאורי האש Borei me'orei ha'eish is a שבח, shevach, it
responds to seeing the fire and it comes after. So you really
don't have to do this anyway, I mean if you're getting your
seeing it directly, but if you're going to do this you're supposed
to do it before you make the ברכה, bracha, not after. So
that's the difference between ברכת המצוה, birchas hamitzvah, ברכת הנהנין birchas hanehenin
before, ברכת השבח birchas hashevach after. Now we have to end with
an exception. Let's take a look. בי רב אמרי, Bei Rav amri,
in the house of רב Rav they say חוץ מן הטבילה ושופר,
chutz min hatvila v'shofar, the exclusion is טבילה tvila and שופר. shofar.
Those you actually make after. Now we don't now טבילה דאכתי גברא
לא חזי, tvila d'achati gavra lo chazi, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: בשלמא טבילה, Bishlama tvila, I get טבילה tvila דאכתי גברא
לא חזי d'achati gavra lo chazi because the person isn't fit to
make the ברכה bracha yet. Why not? I'll get back to it
in a minute. אלא שופר מאי טעמא? Ella shofar mai ta'ama? שופר,
Shofar, why not make it before? וכי תימא משום דילמא מקלקל תקיעה,
v'chi teima mishum dilma mekalkel tekiya, maybe you'll mess it up and
you won't successfully do the תקיעה? tekiya? אי הכי אפילו שחיטה ומילה
נמי? Ee hachi afilu shechita u'mila nami? So anything you can mess
up, שחיטה, shechita, מילה, mila, I hope not, but anyway.
What was this חוץ מן
השופר?
chutz
min hashofar?
So that's so okay, the גמרא's Gemara not done. אלא אמר רב
חסדא חוץ מן הטבילה בלבד. Ella amar Rav Chisda chutz min hatvila
bilvad. Fine, strike out שופר. shofar. Okay, there's no good reason make
שופר shofar different. טבילה Tvila is the one exception. איתמר נמי, Ismar
nami, it was also taught
איתמר ismar בלבד איתמר, bilvad ismar, I'm sorry. So it was only
said חוץ מן הטבילה, chutz min hatvila, strike out
שופר. shofar. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly, טבל
ועלה, taval v'ala, you went in the מקוה mikvah and you came
out, בעלייתו אומר, ba'aliyaso omer, when you come out you say ברוך
אשר קדשנו במצוותיו וציוונו על הטבילה. Baruch asher kidshanu b'mitzvosav v'tzivanu al
hatvila. Now why is גברא לא חזי? gavra lo chazi? So there's
an interesting debate. Some say, רש"י Rashi says, we're talking about a
גר, ger, and a גר ger can't make the ברכה bracha yet
because he's not yet מצווה, metzuveh, so he has to make it
after. תוספות Tosfos says no, we're talking about תקנת עזרא, takanas Ezra,
which was that after a man was a בעל קרי, ba'al keri,
he couldn't say a ברכה. bracha. So for him, for men being
טובל, tovel, they would have to say it afterwards. Which would mean
nowadays, well first of all men don't make the ברכה bracha anyway
because we're not doing it, but but how about something that is
like for people other than the גר ger and a man for
בעל קרי, ba'al keri, like a woman? So there's a מחלוקת ראשונים.
machlokes Rishonim. Some say women make it before, because this is only
excluding the cases that need to be excluded, going back to the
question of do we make distinctions based on case? And some say
no, once for some cases we say it after, we always say
it after. So ספרדי Sfaradi women I believe say it before,
אשכנזי Ashkenazi women dunk,
put their head out of the water, say the ברכה bracha and
then dunk again. Okay, so they get it both like the before
and the after, but that's an interesting question because here the גמרא
Gemara is so clearly not talking about women, it's talking about men,
and it's either about the גר ger scenario or about the בעל
קרי ba'al keri scenario. Okay. That went fine and better than
expected and I'm going to make weight. Do I have to make
a ברכה?
bracha? I don't know, probably does not.